<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reasons humbly offered to be considered before the Act for Printing be renewed (unless with alterations) viz. for freedom of trade in lawful books, and setting severe penalties on scandalous and seditious books against the government</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58261</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R548A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217973</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829604</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829604</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34044</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58261)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34044)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1998:7, 21242:47)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reasons humbly offered to be considered before the Act for Printing be renewed (unless with alterations) viz. for freedom of trade in lawful books, and setting severe penalties on scandalous and seditious books against the government</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library (reel 1998) and the British Library (reel 2124.2).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Censorship --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34044:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Reaſons humbly offered to be conſidered before <hi>the Act for Printing</hi> be renewed (unleſs with Alterations) <hi>viz.</hi> for Freedom of Trade in Lawful Books, and ſetting ſevere Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties on Scandalous and Seditious Books againſt the Government.</head>
            <p>THE Trade of Printing hath been an Ancient Manufacture of this Kingdom (and as ſuch) fit to be Encouraged for the publick good; yet by that Act, and the great Powers thereby given, or at leaſt colourably thence taken, by the Maſters and Wardens of the Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners Company and other Patentees, to the very great Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, and publick Damage of the Nation, by inhauncing the Price of Books, and alſo to the Impoveriſhment of the generality of the Members of that Company, <hi>viz.</hi> Printers, Bookſellers, Book-binders, Haberdaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and ſeveral other conſiderable Traders, who have been thereby reſtrained from the moſt beneficial part of their Ancient Trade and Right by their Apprenticeſhip.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> I. about the thirteenth Year of his Reign, granted to the Maſter, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and Comminalty of the Myſtery of Stationers, <hi>London,</hi> a Patent of Priviledge to Print, Utter and Sell all manner of Primers, Pſalters, Pſalms, Almanacks, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Books, for ever, with a Clauſe of Prohibition to all others; therein alſo giving Power to the ſaid Maſter, Wardens and Aſſiſtants to make By-Laws for the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement of the ſaid Patent; who have ſo effectually contrived their own Profit therein, that for thirty Years laſt paſt they have conſtantly divided above 12 <hi>l. per cent.</hi> yearly, beſides other frequent and more private Dividends, and extravagantly chargable Feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, out of the Profits of the thus monopolized Trade (excluding the generality of the Members of that Company from any Benefit of the ſaid Patent, though it was grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the whole Body.)</p>
            <p>In the year 1662. they did, by the Solicitation of Sir <hi>R. Leſtrange,</hi> obtain the ſaid Act, under the ſpecious Colour of <hi>Preventing Seditious, Scandalous, and Treaſonable Books,</hi> &amp;c. which indeed was principally by them deſigned to ſupport their intended Monopoly; for in a very ſhort Time after they purchaſed into their Hands ſeveral other Patents, which they had ſet Agents on to beg of the then King: To purchaſe which Patents they have engag'd the Corporations Inheritance, and brought a Rent-charge thereon to almoſt 600 <hi>l. per ann.</hi> to the very great Injury of the Corporation in general, to ſerve a particular End. And then confederating with other Patentees, Bibles and the generality of other Books of publick and general uſe were got into Patents, and that ſo comprehenſive, that near ſeventy ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Books were got into one Patent, and thereby advanced to above double the Price they were ſold for before. And to ſecure their Monopoly from expiring, and to tye up the Crown therein from inveſting any others during that Time, they obtained two or three Patents for the ſame Books, to take place in Reverſion almoſt to an hundred Years to come. Our own Printers being thus reſtrained, the greateſt part of the Printing-trade was carried hence into <hi>Holland, viz.</hi> Engliſh Bibles, Common-Prayer Books, Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Pſalters, Grammars, Almanacks, and multitudes of other Books of general and perpetual uſe, and from thence exported to all our Foreign Plantations, <hi>Ireland, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and alſo hither, for the gain of above <hi>cent. per cent.</hi> to the Traders therein.</p>
            <p>Vaſt Quantities of theſe Books have been ſeized by theſe Patentees, who beſides Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zure, did alſo proſecute the Perſons in whoſe Hands they found them, by vertue of the ſaid Act; and thereby extorted exorbitant Sums of Mony, beyond the Penalty of the ſaid Act, they having taken Care to have the Penalty of their thus monopoliz'd Books aſcertained by the ſaid Act, the Penalty being 6 <hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d. per</hi> Book: But Seditious and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Books they were thereby only charged as an Offence againſt the ſaid Act, which was an Offence by other Laws before that Act, and will be ſo when it is expired.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:34044:2"/>
            <p>Theſe Patentees, after having, as aforeſaid, by Seizure amaſſed great numbers of theſe <hi>Holland</hi> printed Books, they on purpoſe forbear to furniſh the Market with the ſame of their own Printing (all other Printers being by the ſaid Act reſtrained from that part of Trade) have to a thus empty Market ſold again the ſaid ſeized Books; and have further reſeized the very ſame Books themſelves ſold, and likewiſe proſecuted the Perſons again in whoſe Hands they found them, extorting from them the Penalty of the ſaid Act of 6 <hi>s</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi> to the utter Ruin of many conſiderable Merchants and other Traders. They having procured an Agent of their own (whom, for his Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, they made Partner in this their Monopoly) to be made Meſſenger of the Preſs, under the ſpecious Pretence of ſerving the Government in ſuppreſſing Seditious Books; which was only a Colour to carry on the Ends aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>They joyned together, and bought three Horſes, and ſent the Clark and Beadle, the Servants of the Maſter and Wardens, and a Secretary's Meſſenger, to ride all <hi>England</hi> over, to ſeize on the Books in their Patents, which they alledged to be counterfeit; Who did ſeize accordingly, though on many of ſuch as were of their own Printing: And after two or three Months Ravage they returned back, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Account to the ſaid Maſter and Wardens, and the other Patentees, what Books, and from whom they had ſeized them. Theſe Patentees ſent Writs out of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> and <hi>King's-bench</hi> to proſecute the Perſons from whom they had ſeized, upon the Penalty of the ſaid Act (many of which) Books, thus ſeized, had been before ſold by the Plaintiffs, in the Proſecution; and did force exorbitant Compoſitions.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>John Jekil</hi> ſtood Trial for about 25 Bibles, before Judge <hi>Hales,</hi> and was caſt upon the ſaid Act, and paid 6 <hi>s</hi> 8 <hi>d per</hi> Book for the Bible to one Patentee, and 6 <hi>s</hi> 8 <hi>d. per</hi> Book for the Pſalms to the other Patentees; though but one Book, yet thus divided, made two Penalties, Mr. <hi>Jekil</hi> paid about fifty Pounds Coſts and Forfeitures. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Times theſe Bibles had been ſeized before they came to Mr. <hi>Jekil</hi>'s Hand, and how many times they have been ſold and ſeized ſince is worthy conſideration; and this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed under the Authority of that Act.</p>
            <p>The Noiſe of Mr. <hi>Jekil</hi>'s Judgment upon his Trial, coming abroad into the Countries, to the Knowledg of thoſe proſecuted there, frighted them ſo that ſome came up to Town, and others ſent to their Correſpondents and Friends here, to compound with the Proſecutors at any Rate; whoſe Compoſition was uſually 6 <hi>s</hi> 8 <hi>d per</hi> Book, and 40 or 50 Shillings for pretended Charge of Seizure and Proſecution: But if a Bible had the Common Prayer in it, then there were three times 6 <hi>s</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi> Compoſition Mony, <hi>viz.</hi> Bible, Common Prayer and Pſalms; how much of which hath come to the King (half being his due) the Records thereof in the <hi>Exchequer</hi> may ſhew.</p>
            <p>It is ſuggeſted in the ſaid Act, That the Trade of Printing is over-charged with Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and therefore fit to have their Number retrenched; which is Enacted accordingly thereby.</p>
            <p>To which is humbly ſuppoſed, That if the Manufacture of Printing were left free, as other Trades, it would employ above double the number of Printers that are in <hi>England,</hi> and that on Lawful Work too. For, ſince the Year 1662. (when the Act was made) there have more Engliſh Bibles, and other Engliſh Books, been printed in <hi>Holland,</hi> by one <hi>Athias</hi> a Jew, (among many other Printers there) than have been printed by any four Printers in <hi>England</hi> in that Time; which <hi>Holland</hi>-printed Engliſh Books have been merchandized to us, and to the King's Subjects in our Plantations abroad, which might have been ſo done from hence, had they been afforded here at the ſame reaſonable Rates: Which they might have been had the Trade been free. Freedom of Printing here would ſoon produce a Manufacture to export as well to our Plantations as to thoſe very Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries who now furniſh us and them, whereby the King's Cuſtoms would be advanced by Paper imported and Books exported, the Merchant enrich'd, and the Printer and Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binder, and many other Trades employed, which by theſe Monopolies have been hitherto fruſtrated. Theſe Books being prohibited are always imported by Stealth, ſo that the King is always defrauded in his Cuſtomes.</p>
            <p>The Government of all the Printing in <hi>England</hi> (except the two Univerſities) is by the ſaid Act veſted into the Hands of the ſaid Maſter and Wardens, who to gain the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities alſo into their Hands have farmed the whole Printing in <hi>Cambridg:</hi> And in the year 1688. did petition King <hi>James</hi> (under pretence to be enabled to ſuppreſs ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Books, their old Stalking-horſe) That they might, in his Majeſty's Name proſecute the <hi>Oxford</hi>-printing by a <hi>Quo Warranto,</hi> which being granted by the ſaid King, the Maſter,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34044:2"/>Wardens Aſſiſtants and the other Patentees did ſolicit <hi>Father Peters</hi> and other ſuch fit In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, to promote the ſame; And in return of this Service (beſides Cluſters of Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas) they ſuffered their publik Ware-houſe-keeper, to propagate to Sale their Popiſh Books, which was notified to their Party all over the Nation, as a happy Omen of its ſpeedy Converſion to the Catholick Faith, their Books were now freely printed and ſold by the Governours of that Company at their Common Hall: Which Proſecution was carried on at the joynt Charge of theſe Patentees, who have ſince uſed other means to get the <hi>Oxford</hi> printing into their Hands; for about twelve Months ſince they did ſo far endear themſelves to Dr. <hi>Edwards</hi> and Dr. <hi>Aldrich,</hi> one Vice-chancellor of <hi>Oxford</hi> laſt Year, the other this, to whom they gave Bond of many thouſand Pounds Penalty to ſave them harmleſs in the diſpoſeſſing the Univerſity's Printers, and farming the ſame to theſe Patentees (who had kept down the Price of Books to one third of what theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentees ſold them at before) which the ſaid Vice-chanchellors did undertake and effect, though contrary to the general Inclination of that venerable Body, whereby above 35000 Bibles, and many thouſands of other Books three quarters finiſhed, were rendred waſte Paper, And twenty or thirty Families, that for twelve or fourteen years laſt paſt have been maintained by this Manufacture in <hi>Oxford,</hi> are many of them now utterly ruined, to make way for preſent Sale of many Thouſands of their formerly ſeized <hi>Holland</hi> printed Books, and for the riſe of Books printed by theſe Patentees; which are already advanced one third Penny, and are threatned to be raiſed double, if the Act be renewed: which <hi>Holland</hi> Books (by the renewal of the ſaid Act) may be re-ſeized, and Proſecutions made again (though ſold by theſe Patentees) as they formerly have done many times over.</p>
            <p>They are now Zealous to get that Act renewed, that they may be enabled to continue theſe Practices, and to tax the Publick, as they have done for 30 years paſt. They have thus long taxed the Nation 1500 <hi>l.</hi> and upwards yearly, in the Almanack Trade on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and this is their aim in getting the Act renewed, they do thereby ſell that for three Pence, which at one Penny would be a ſufficient Trading price, and ſufficiently gainful. They do likewiſe diſcourage Authors, who, for Commenting or Expounding upon part of a Book, which is their Text (as they uſe the Term) muſt be conſtrained to pay them a Premium for it, or be forced to fell their Works to them, though but for one fourth of what others would give, if they had the freedom to Print them; which none will dare to do (if that Act be renewed.) Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pool,</hi> and many other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend and Learned Authors have been compelled to pay them their extravagant De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, for uſing the Bible Text to Comment upon (tho' but a ſmall part thereof, as the Book of <hi>Pſalms,</hi> &amp;c.) The like practiſed upon <hi>Virgil, Ovid, Terence,</hi> &amp;c. or any of the old Claſſick School-books which were got into their Patents; in ſome of which the ſole Printing of 50 or 60 were contained.</p>
            <p>By the ſaid Act it is Enacted, That a Book being Licenſed and Entred into the Regiſter Book of the Company of Stationers, it is forbid to be Printed without the Owners Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence (who by Vertue of that Entry is Owner) under the Penalty of 6 <hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d. per</hi> Book; which Regiſter hath (by the undue Practices of the Maſter and Wardens) been ſo ill kept, that many Entries have been unduly made; inſomuch, that the true Proprietors both by Purchaſe, Licenſe and Entry, all duly made of ſeveral Books, which afterwards have been eraſed, or the Leaves wherein they were written, have been cut out, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due Entries made to others who had no right; which is directly contrary to the plain words and meaning of the ſaid Act; whereby the Owners have not only been defrauded of their Right, but alſo rendred liable to the Penalty of 6 <hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d. per</hi> Book, for all the Books they Printed, Sold or Bound. Many learned Authors have been defrauded of their Rights thereby, who, after many years Pains and Study, and afterwards by a bare Delivery of their Books to be Licenſed or Tranſcribed, have been barred by ſurrepitious Entries made in the ſaid Regiſter (to inſtance in the Book called <hi>Regula Placitandi,</hi> among many others, written by a learned Lawyer and worthy Member of this Parliament.) Wherefore, it is humbly repreſented whether the Irregularities, aforeſaid, may not have rendred the Act impracticable to be executed, agreeable to Juſtice and Equity; and if the Act be renewed, if it may not eſtabliſh a wrongful Poſſeſſion, unleſs that Regiſter be firſt duly rectified.</p>
            <p>The Property of Engliſh Authors hath been always owned as Sacred among the Traders, and generally forborn, hitherto, to be invaded; but if any ſhould invade ſuch Properties, there is remedy, by Laws already made, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34044:3"/>no other were ever thought needful till 1662. The Works of <hi>Homer, Heſiod, Horace, Ovid, Virgil, Caeſar, Lucan, Plautus, Tully, Florus, Curtius,</hi> and Multitudes of other ancient Claſſick Authors, which were always free to all Printers and Bookſellers to Print, before the making of the ſaid Act; but ſince are got into Patents, and by that Act prohibited from being Printed, under the Penalty of 6 <hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d. per</hi> Book, to the inhanſing the Prices, the hinderance of the Printer, and are only an encouragement for Foreigners to import upon us; which are the Grievances long endured, and now complained of; and humbly Prayed to be conſidered, before the Act for Printing be continued.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid, The Charter to the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> for Printing of all manner of Books (which the Maſter, Wardens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have now farmed into their own Hands) is now propoſed to be confirmed in Parliament: Which Charter (if confirmed without a ſaving to every Man his particular Property) ſeems to defeat all particular Properties; in Copies, both in reſpect to Bookſellers and Authors, and makes the Owners liable to the Penalties in that Charter, which are very ſevere, beſides the loſs of their Property; the Patentees will agree the ſaving of Patent-books, peradventure, well enough; but will readily conſent that particular Property may be gain'd into their Controle.</p>
            <p>Till the year, 1662. it was not thought needful, by any precedent Parliament of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> to make an Act for to regulate or reſtrain Printing more than other Trades, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth that Act inflict any new Penalty for ſeditious Books, but leaves them to the former Laws. About the beginning of the Popiſh Plot, this Act was diſcontinued; and Sir <hi>Roger Leſtrange,</hi> Surveyor of the Preſs, and the Meſſenger of the Preſs, were both ſeverely cenſured in Parliament, and that Act was not thought fit to be renewed till the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign; where Sir <hi>Roger Leſtrange,</hi> being a Member of Parliament, got the ſaid Act to be renewed.</p>
            <p>Now (if the Tables were turned) That ſcandalous and ſeditious Books, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were forbid, under the Penalty of 6 <hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi> or 100 <hi>l. per</hi> Book; and Books thus monopolized, by Patents, were left to the determination of the Law; it is humbly preſumed, the Government would be much leſs peſtered with them than heretofore; neither would there be need to charge the Government with two hundred Pound <hi>per Annum</hi> for a Surveyor of the Preſs, nor fifty Pound <hi>per Annum</hi> for a Meſſenger of the Preſs, as it was formerly to Sir <hi>Roger Leſtrange</hi> (if it be not ſtill done ſo to others.) If Books Mechanical, Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, Trade, Cookery, Husbandry, Phiſick, Surgery, Geography, and the like, were not required to be Licenſed, the Biſhops Chaplains would be ſo much the leſs diſturbed from their Studies; and it is humbly preſumed the Government can ſcarcely be harmed thereby.</p>
            <p>By that Act Printers are reſtrained from ſetting up their Trades, to which they ſerved their Apprentiſhip; whereby Multitudes of them have been forced to go to <hi>Holland</hi> and other Countries, to work as Journy-men there, in Printing Engliſh Bibles and other Engliſh Books; vaſt numbers whereof, have been brought over into <hi>England</hi> by Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, for gain; one Merchant (among many others) importing near twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Engliſh Bibles yearly, beſides vaſt quantities of our Engliſh Books, that were got into Patents, and reſtrained by the ſaid Act, under the Penalty aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>All which Matters are humbly offered to be conſidered (before the ſaid Act be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) by many hundreds of Traders in the ſaid Manufacture, who by having freedom to follow their Trades on lawful Work, ſhall not be neceſſitated to betake themſelves (for a Livelihood) to unlawful Work, as too many have been forced to do, or to turn Port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers or ſome other ſervile Employments, which their Parents and Friends little dreamed of when they placed them Apprentices to their Trades.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:34044:3"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
